T. Harrison and John Work Garrett papers, circa 1875-1942
ANS Archives
T. Harrison and John Work Garrett papers
circa 1875-1942
Correspondence of T. Harrison Garrett and John Work Garrett, and John Work Garrett’s handwritten card file documenting the Garrett coin collection.
American Numismatic Society
5.3 cubic feet (20 boxes)
Organization of the Papers
Organized in four series: 1. Correspondence, 1875-1942, 2. Rome Correspondence, 1929-1932, 3. Catalogs and Inventories, 4. Card Indexes
Biographical Note
T. Harrison Garrett (1848-1888), whose family managed the Baltimore & Ohio Railroad, began collecting coins as a student at Princeton in the 1860s. His son, John Work Garrett (1872-1942), greatly expanded the collection. John joined the American Numismatic Society (ANS) in 1920, and in 1921 was elected fellow. He served as member of the Council (now the Board of Trustees) of ANS from 1921 to 1929. John graduated from Princeton in 1895 and was a career diplomat, serving as secretary of the American Legation at the Hague beginning in 1901 and ambassador to Italy from 1929 to 1934. Following an unsuccessful bid for a U.S. Senate nomination in 1922, he retired to Evergreen House, the family estate in Baltimore. Upon his death in 1942, the estate, along with the family’s numismatic and other collections, were left to Johns Hopkins University, where he served as a trustee from 1937 to 1942. The University auctioned off most of the numismatic collection in the 1970s and 1980s.
Provenance
The Garrett papers were donated by Johns Hopkins University to the ANS in January 2000 through the efforts of David and Susan Tripp.
Access
Collection open to all researchers.
Custodial History
When John Work Garrett died in 1942, all of his collections were left to Johns Hopkins University. The papers were kept there until they were donated to the ANS in 2000.
Coins, American--New Jersey; Copper coins--New Jersey; Tokens--Collectors and collecting; Garrett, T. Harrison (Thomas Harrison), 1848-1888; Garrett, John Work, 1872-1942; Garrett, Robert Work, 1875-1961; Low, Lyman Haynes, 1844-1924; Maris, Edward, 1832-1900; Paquet, Anthony C., 1814-1882; Chapman, Henry, 1859-1935; Chapman, S.H. (Samuel Hudson), 1869-1949; Frossard, Edouard, 1837-1899; Mehl, B. Max (Benjamin Max), 1884-1957; Forrer, Leonard; Raymond, Wayte, 1886-1956; Cogan, George W.; Cogan, Edward D., 1803-1884; Massamore, George 1845-1898; Schulman, Hans M. F. (Hans Moritz Friedrich), 1913-1990; Schulman, Jacques; Jacques Schulman (Firm); Correspondence; Notebooks; Inventories; Photographs; Card indexes
Scope and Content Note
Contains correspondence of T. Harrison Garrett and John Work Garrett, which includes a letter from Edward Maris to T. Harrison Garrett offering him his collection of New Jersey Coppers; correspondence with Lyman H. Low, including a letter indicating the transfer of Low’s collection of Hard Times Tokens; a letter from Anthony C. Paquet regarding a dollar he designed; letters informing John of his election the American Numismatic Society and his subsequent election as a fellow; and extensive correspondence with U.S. and foreign dealers, including Henry and Samuel Chapman, Edouard Frossard, B. Max Mehl, Leonard Forrer, Wayte Raymond, Edward and George Cogan, George Massamore, and Jacques and Hans Schulman. While most of the correspondence and documents relate to T. Harrison and John, a few items concern T. Harrison’s other son, Robert Work Garrett (1875-1961). Also included are T. Harrison's and John Work Garrett’s notebooks and a handwritten card file documenting the Garrett coin collection, including information on price paid and provenance; photographic negatives taken by the Johns Hopkins University Numismatic Curator, Sarah Elizabeth Freman; and a typed and annotated catalog of the collection prepared by the Chapman Brothers between 1905 and 1907. Some of the 19th century correspondence was lost in a Baltimore fire in 1904.
- Box 1 of 20: Series 1, Correspondence, 1875-1942
  - A (J.W.G)
  - Adams, Edgar H., 1920-1933 (J.W.G.)
  - American Numismatic Society, 1920-1923 (J.W.G.)
  - American Numismatic Society, 1924-1928 (J.W.G.)
  - American Numismatic Society, 1929-1939 (J.W.G.)
  - American Numismatic Association, 1920-1929 (J.W.G.)
  - American Numismatic and Archaeological Society, 1883 (T.H.G.)
  - Ars Classica, 1925-1927 (J.W.G.)
  - Baldwin and Frick, 1922 (J.W.G.)
  - Baldwin, A.H. and Sons, 1927-1928 (J.W.G.)
  - Baltimore Coin Club, 1935 (J.W.G.)
  - Bangs and Co. (T.H.G.)
  - C.H. Bechtel, Dealer (T.H.G.)
  - Beistle Co., 1925-1929 (J.W.G.)
  - Belmont, August, 1923-1924 (J.W.G.)
  - Bernard, Nellie G., 1887 (T.H.G.)
  - Bovier, Charles, 1885 (T.H.G.)
  - Brett, Homer, 1931 (J.W.G.)
  - British Museum Sales, 1883 (T.H.G.)
  - Brown, Alex and Sons, 1921-1929 (J.W.G.)
  - Brown, William P., 1889 (T.H.G.)
  - Caetani, Gelasio, 1923 (J.W.G.)
  - Cahn, Adolph E., 1925 (J.W.G.)
  - Caldwell, Raymond L., 1935 (J.W.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1879-1885 (T.H.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1904-1905 (R.G.)
- Box 2 of 20: Series 1, Correspondence, 1875-1942 (continued)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1906-1907 (R.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1908-1910 (R.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1911-1913 (R.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1914-1916 (R.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1917-1919 (R.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1919-1920 (R.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman, 1921-1923 (R.G.)
- Box 3 of 20: Series 1, Correspondence, 1875-1942 (continued)
  - S. H. and H. Chapman, 1924-1925 (J.W.G.)
  - S. H. and H. Chapman, 1926-1932 (J.W.G.)
  - S.H. and H. Chapman: Garrett Catalogue I
  - S.H. and H. Chapman: Garrett Catalogue II
  - Clapp, C. E., 1934 (J.W.G.)
  - Clark, T. James, 1923-1931 (J.W.G.)
  - G. W. Cogan, 1879-1883 1879 (T.H.G)
  - T. S. Collier, 1879 (T.H.G)
  - T. L. Elder, 1920-1924 (J.W.G.)
  - Ellsworth Collection, 1924 (J.W.G.)
  - Elliot, George M., 1879 (T.H.G)
  - E. Frossard, 1882-1886 (T.H.G)
  - R. Gaettens, 1925 (J.W.G.)
  - Garrett Collections, Regulations (J.W.G.)
  - General Correspondence, 1931-1941 (J.W.G.)
  - R. Gimpel, 1925 (J.W.G.)
- Box 4 of 20: Series 1, Correspondence, 1875-1942 (continued)
  - Garrett Collection
  - Guttag Brothers, 1923-1924 (J.W.G.)
  - Guttag Brothers, 1925-1928 (J.W.G.)
  - Ferguson Haines, 1879 (T.H.G.)
  - Haseltine, 1879-1887 (T.H.G.)
  - Henkels and Tripple, 1882 (T.H.G.)
  - Hesslein, 1919-1928 (J.W.G.)
  - Jenkins, Michael, 1911 (J.W.G.)
  - Kernan, Eugene T., 1921 (J.W.G.)
  - Knoedler, M. and Co., 1923 (J.W.G.)
  - Kohler, Rud., 1925-1927 (J.W.G.)
  - Krausz, S., 1920 (J.W.G.)
  - Leary and Co., 1879 (T.H.G.)
  - Geo. A. Leavitt and Co., 1878-1883 (T.H.G.)
  - Lincoln and Son, n.d. (T.H.G.)
  - List of coins, num. 1 to 17, n.d. (J.W.G.)
  - List of coins, num. 18 to 45, n.d. (J.W.G.)
  - Low, Lyman H., 1883-1886 (T.H.G.)
  - Low, Lyman H., 1922 (J.W.G.)
  - Luthi, F. C. and Co., 1922 (J.W.G.)
  - Marie of Greece, 1935 (J.W.G.)
  - Maris, E., 1885 (T.H.G.)
  - Massamore, Geo., 1882-1888 (T.H.G.)
- Box 5 of 20: Series 1, Correspondence, 1875-1942 (continued)
  - Mehl, B. Max, 1920-1923 (J.W.G.)
  - Mehl, B. Max, 1924-1927 (J.W.G.)
  - Mehl, B. Max, 1928-1940 (J.W.G.)
  - Miller, William K., 1881 (T.H.G.)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1880-1888 (T.H.G.)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1903-1917 (R.G.)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1921-1937 (J.W.G.)
  - Mitchell and Ferris, 1921 (J.W.G.)
  - Newcomer and Co., 1921-1927 (J.W.G.)
  - New Jersey Historical Society, 1932 (J.W.G.)
  - Newlin, H. P., 1883-1886 (T.H.G.)
  - New York Coin and Stamp Co., 1919 (J.W.G.)
  - P. L. Club, 1923 (J.W.G.)
  - Paquet, A. C., 1877 (T.H.G.)
  - Photographs taken for Garrett
  - Princeton University, 1921-1922 (J.W.G.)
  - Proskey Brothers, 1884 (T.H.G.)
  - Rakitch, M. M., 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Randall J. Colvin, 1879 (T.H.G.)
- Box 6 of 20: Series 1, Correspondence, 1875-1942 (continued)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1919-1921 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1922-1923 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1922 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1923 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1924 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1925 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1926-1928 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1929-1934 (J.W.G.)
  - Raymond, Wayte, 1935-1941 (J.W.G.)
  - Robinson, David M., 1930-1931 (J.W.G.)
  - Sampson, H. G., 1879 (T.H.G.)
  - St. Louis Stamp and Coin Co., 1922-1938 (J.W.G.)
  - Schulman, J., 1916-1927 (J.W.G.)
  - Schulman, J., 1928-1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Schulman, J., 1931-1940 (J.W.G.)
  - Scott and Co., 1879, 1883 (T.H.G.)
- Box 7 of 20: Series 1, Correspondence, 1875-1942 (continued)
  - Seaby, B. A., 1926 (J.W.G.)
  - Sears, Elmer S., 1925 (J.W.G.)
  - Seemuller, William, 1883 (T.H.G.)
  - Seltman, C. T., 1926-1929 (J.W.G.)
  - Smith, Harlan P., 1884-1885 (T.H.G.)
  - Spink and Son, 1923-1925 (J.W.G.)
  - Spink and Son, 1926-1928 (J.W.G.)
  - Spink and Son, 1929-1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Spink and Son, 1931-1939 (J.W.G.)
  - Steigerwalt, Charles, 1882-1883 (T.H.G.)
  - Stowell Printing Co., 1921 (J.W.G.)
  - Sullivan Brothers and Libbie, 1883
  - Robert Taylor, c.1878-1879 (T.H.G.)
  - U. S. Treasury: Mint Proof Sets, 1915 (T.H.G.)
  - U. S. Treasury: Mint Proof Sets, 1879-1888 (J.W.G.)
  - U.S. Colonial
  - U.S. Half Cents
  - U.S. Large Cents
  - U.S. 20¢, 10¢, 3¢, 2¢, 1¢
  - U.S. Silver Dollars, 1/2, 1/4
  - U.S. Commemorative Coins
  - U.S. Pattern and Trail
  - U.S. Private and Territorial
  - U.S. Gold
  - van Aalst, 1920 (J.W.G.)
  - Voos, F. W., 1926-1927 (J.W.G.)
  - Woodward, W. Elliot, 1882-1886 (T.H.G.)
  - Wuesthoff, A., 1884 (J.W.G.)
- Box 8 of 20: Series 2, Rome Correspondence, 1929-1932; Series 3, Catalogs and Inventories
  - Rome: American Numismatic Association, 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Michele Baranowsky, 1931 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Henry Chapman, 1929 (J.W.G)
  - Rome: Cohen Collection, 1929-1930 (R.G.)
  - Rome: Dr. Joseph Marshall Flint, 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Albert Gallatin, 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: General, 1929? (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Daniel Kellad, 1929 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: E.D. Klotz (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Fred Konold, 1931 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: R.V.D. Magoffin, 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Massachusetts Historical Society, 1932 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: B. Max Mehl, 1931 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Thomas Murray, 1932 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Purchases
  - Rome: Rakitch, 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: J. Schulman, 1932 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Max Sioli, 1929? (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Spink and Son, 1931-1932 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Royall Tyler, 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Mario Verga, 1930 (J.W.G.)
  - Rome: Shirley H. Weber, 1929 (J.W.G.)
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Awards and Decorations (List by SEF)
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Byzantium, Goths, Franks, France, England, Italy
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Collections of Lepere, Coleman, Zimmerman, and Wilcox, Greek, Roman, European and United States
  - Catalogs and Inventories: English, French, Spanish, Mexican, South American, Italian, Swiss, Sicilian
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Europe
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Europe, Asia, Africa
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Europe, Asia, Africa, North America, South America, Australia
- Box 9 of 20: Series 3, Catalogs and Inventories (continued)
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Europe, Asia, Rome, United States
  - Catalogs and Inventories: J. W. G. handwritten
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Rome
  - Catalogs and Inventories: United States
  - Catalogs and Inventories: United States
  - Catalogs and Inventories: United States
- Box 10 of 20: Series 3, Catalogs and Inventories (continued)
  - Catalogs and Inventories: United States
  - Catalogs and Inventories: United States, Colonial, Continental, Confederate Currency, and U. S. Fractional Currency
  - Catalogs and Inventories: United States and Foreign Medals
  - Catalogs and Inventories: Washington
  - To go to Merc, J.W. G.
  - J. W. G. Reference
- Box 11 of 20: Brittle originals
- Box 12 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes
  Campania; Auriol Find; Calagria; Lucania; Bruttium; Sicily; Syracuse; Macedon and Thrace; Kings; Thrace; N. Greece; Boeotia; Athens; Aegina; Corinth; Peloponnesus; Crete; Pontus; Paphlagonia; Bithynia; Mysia; Troas Aeolis Lesgos; Ionia; Caria; Lydia Cappadocia; Bactria; Seleucids; Phoenicia; Egypt; Cyrenaica; Carthage; Numidia-Mauretania; Greek Imperial; Latin-Orient; Hispania Gaul; Macedon Thrace; Greece; Asia-Minor; Syria-Phoenicia; Africa; Republic Rome; Consular; Italy; Provinces; Triumvirate; Romano-Campania; Empire; 100-; 200-; 300-; 400-; Contorniates and Tesseres; Inferior AR and AE; Aes grave; Aes; Apulia; Picenum; Umbria; Etruria etc.; Byzantine A/, AR, AE.
- Box 13 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Tray 50: Byzantine; Tray 60: Arabic; Orthodox Caliphs; Moors in Spain; North Africa; Egypt-Syria Mesopotamia; Seljuks and Turks; Mongols; Transoxiana; Mohammedans in Persia; Mohammedans in Persia (cont.); Tray 62: Turkey and Persia; A.D. 228-651; Shahs; Afganistan; Tray 63: China; Tray 66: India; Kushanas; Guptas; Sultans of Dehli; Moguls; British; Tray 64: Japan; Tray 67: India and Indochina; French-Portuguese, Dutch-Danish; Assam-Bhutan, Burma-Ceylon-Nepal; Arabia; Indochina; British possessions in Europe; Tokens; Canada; Australia; Not finished 68; East Indies Netherlands; British Borneo etc.; Philippines and Hawaii; Africa independent; Siberia; Malaya; Siam Laos; Persia; Parthians.
- Box 14 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Feudal; Missing; WM. The conqueror 1066-, WM. II Rufus 1087-, Henry I, Beauclerc 1100-, Stephen 1125-1154; Tray 123: England; Austria and Hungary; Czechoslovakia; Switzerland; Baltic States; Siege pieces; Scandinavia; Early AR H. R. E.; H.R.E. (cont.); British; French; Portuguese; Spanish, Danish, Italian, and German; Germany; Tray 101; Burgundians; Salerno etc.; Merovingians; Tray 102; Ostrogoths; Visigoths; Vandals; Suevi; Tray 103; Tray 104: Carolingians; Tray 108: Balkans, Austria, H. R. E., Czechoslovakia; Tray 109; Tray 110; Tray 111; Tray 112; Tray 113; Tray 114.
- Box 15 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Tray 115; Tray 116; Tray 117: Siege pieces; Tray 118: Italy; Tray 119: Italy, Vatican; Tray 120: Vatican, France; Bourbons; Tray 121; Second Empire; Third Republic; Tray 122: France-Feudal; Normans; Tray 123: England; Tray 126: English Colonies; Plantagenets; Lancaster and York; Anglo-Gallic; Scotland; Barbarians; Ireland; Tudors; Stuarts; Tray 58 and 59: Maynard; France part of tray 120: Capetians; German; Valois.
- Box 16 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Oregon, Mormon, and Colorado; California; Private issues: Georgia and Carolina; Assay Bars; Wampum; Miscellaneous; Store cards, 1863-1864; Civil War Tokens; Confederate; California 1, 1/2, and 1/4; Commemoratives; Patterns Territorial; Cents: small and large; Half cent; Pattern: Ad; Pattern: #1 AR; Pattern:1/2# AR; For minor; Patterns; New Jersey; Bar cent; Fugios; Confederations; Nova constellation; Early store cards; Early tokens; Foreign coins circulation in American colonies; Castorland: Kentucky; French colonies; Mules; Mississippi Bubble; Massachusetts cent and half cent; New York; Connecticut; Vermont; Maryland: Annapolis and Baltimore town; Massachusetts, 1776; New Hampshire; Carolina; American plantations; Virginia; Connecticut: Grandby; Rosa Americana; New Jersey: Newbie; Maryland; Colonial Massachusetts; Somer Islands; Bungtowns; Dance; West Indies CS; West Indies coined for-; Cuba; Haiti; Dominican Republic; Porto Rico; British; French; Dutch; Danish; Spanish Guyana etc.; Latin America; Argentina.
- Box 17 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Negatives (photographs); Mark Antony; Bolivia; Araucania and Patagonia; Brazil; Central America; Chile; Colombia; Ecuador; Paraguay; Uruguay; Peru; Venezuela; Dutch Brazil; Mexico; Costa Rica; Guatemala; Honduras; Nicaragua; Panama; Salvador; Belize; Tregizond, 1204-1462; Nicaea, 1204-1261; Thessalonica, 1205-1232; Neopatras, 1271-1318.
- Box 18 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Garrett medals; Coins: 46.1.1; Coins: 47.1.1; Coins: 48.1.1; 1959. Box contains negatives.
- Box 19 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Dealers, etc.; Locations; Collections.
- Box 20 of 20: Series 4, Card Indexes (continued)
  Medals.